Contact

2816107028 (Home) deboratx@aol.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ deborasimmons (LinkedIn) www.epec.net/psep/home.cfm (Other) www.sharpc.org (Other)

Top Skills

Mediation

Healthcare

Informatics

Certifications

CCNS And CCRN retired

Honors-Awards

US Department of Health and Human Services, Strategic Health IT Advanced Research Projects Grants and Programs Management Award, May 2011

Publications

A Proposed Protocol for Meaningful Use Audit Documentation

Examining the Copy and Paste Function in the Use of Electronic Health Records

Electronic Record Design Considerations in Responding to Incidences of Highly Infectious Diseases: Clinical Workflows and Exception Handling.

Enteral Feeding Misconnections: A Consortium Position Statement.

Tubing misconnections:

Normalization of deviance.

Debora Simmons PhD RN FAAN

Quality, Safety and Integrity are inseparable .

Houston, Texas Area

Summary

ECRI Patient Safety Organization (PSO) Clinical and Advisory Council & Interdisciplinary Team www.ecri.org the

Healthcare Diversity Council Board http://healthcarediversitycouncil.org

American Association of Medical Instrumentation and International Organization for Standardization (ISO) Expert Committee 2006-present

Texas Center for Quality and Patient Safety PSO Advisory Council

Texas Board of Nursing
Eligibility & Disciplinary Advisory Committee

Experience

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

Assistant Professor

October 2015 - Present (4 years 8 months)

CHI St Lukes Health System Chief Quality Officer and SVP February 2012 - May 2015 (3 years 4 months)

Houston texas

Joined St Lukes Episcopal Health System 2012 as CQO. Successfully managed Meaningful Use attestation >15M. Responsible for infection control,

regulatory affairs, accreditation, informatics, meaningful use, quality reporting, patient experience, board reporting, accreditation.

National Center for Cognitive Informatics and Decision Making in Healthcare

Executive Operations Director May 2010 - January 2012 (1 year 9 months)

http://www.uthouston.edu/nccd/

The National Center for Cognitive Informatics and Decision Making in Healthcare (NCCD) is funded by the Office of the National Coordinator for Health IT under the Strategic Health IT Advanced Research Projects (SHARP) Program, which seeks to support improvements in the quality, safety and efficiency of health care through advanced information technology. NCCD is a consortium of nine institutions led by The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston.

National Center for Cognitive Informatics and Decision Making in Healthcare School of Biomedical Informatics University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston

The Patient Safety Education Project
Associate Director
October 2008 - December 2010 (2 years 3 months)

The Patient Safety Education Project (PSEP TM) combines two high-quality models to advance a national and international patient safety education-dissemination agenda.

First, the U.S. developed a high-impact, conference-based education dissemination project. Using a curriculum driven, train-the-trainer approach grounded in adult learning theory and embedded into social structures to facilitate behavior change, the model has been evaluated and found to be unprecedentedly successful. This model has been used successfully for the Education in Palliative and End-of-life Care (EPEC) Project.

Second, Australia created a national consensus framework for patient safety from which diverse groups could create teaching materials for all levels of health care workers. In addition, PSEP collaborates with many patient safety groups throughout the United States, Australia, and beyond.

Texas A and M Rural and Community Heath Institute Research Scientist March 2009 - May 2010 (1 year 3 months)

University of Texas M D Anderson Cancer Center Associate Director September 2002 - October 2008 (6 years 2 months)

- Responsible for design, analysis, implementation and operations of a voluntary anonymous close call reporting system in UT and other hospitals (www.utccrs.org) with 65,000 reports in the database
- o Member of the technology data core for The University of Texas Center of Excellence for Patient Safety Research and Practice
- Program Director and Analyst: The Healthcare Alliance Safety Partnershipan innovative non punitive error reporting program for registered nurses, the first non punitive healthcare error reporting program in the United States. www.texashasp.org
- o Designed investigation methodology synthesizing IOM recommendations
- o Performed investigations and presented results
- o Responsible for meeting regulatory requirements
- o Wrote research proposal for Board of Nursing and IRBs in multiple institutions
- o Negotiated, wrote and managed multiple partnerships with participating hospitals
- o Reported findings to public meetings of the Board of Nurse Examiners

The Methodist Hospital
Clinical Nurse Specialist
January 2001 - January 2002 (1 year 1 month)

Intelligent Diagnostics
VP Clinical Operations
January 1999 - January 2002 (3 years 1 month)
Bayesian networks

Education

Texas Woman's University PhD, Nursing · (1990 - 2011)

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

MSN, Nursing · (1988 - 1997)

Texas Woman's University PhD, Hard Work · (1987 - 1991)

San Jacinto College ADN, Nursing · (1986 - 1987)

Bear Creek High School · (1970 - 1974)